So.
We did it. CPU is there.
So let's um.
Basically the idea for today is uh to um.
Keep going with the.
Examples of meta programming I'd like to.
Discuss a little bit more than I did
yesterday the aspects of cogeneration.
And also uh.
Try to dig down the relation between the
runtime,
the library and and your code because as
we said.
Meet the programming now has become.
One of the main pillars of of our systems
because we are basically using frameworks
that are.
Are developed and grow on and on to the
point in which you're writing a small
amount of code and your program is GB big.
And so yesterday we basically had the
first overview.
Today we spent some time not introducing
the really new notion,
but we will keep going and learn from
these notions.
OK,
so the first thing I'd like to bring up
again.
Is the whitespace compiler.
Because I mean the white space compiler
is clearly.
A compiler,
but it is also clearly an interesting
example of reflection and technically
reflection and intersection because
actually.
The system Oh no, sorry,
it's not technically an example of
reflection in itself,
because the behaviour of the compiler
does not depend from the user of the
reflection,
but actually it uses the reflection API.
To operate.
And so it's a good example since we
already discussed its purpose to look and
discuss a few other things.
OK, so.
First good thing is that we we we don't
need to explain the purpose of this code
and we can focus on the compile.
Uh method which uh uh.
Is the method responsible for actually
generating the code using the reflection
API?
So it it's oh, here we are.
So the main code basically performs few
things that are interesting for our
purpose.
Because the assembly name is part of the
reflection API and then we will see the
compile method which receives.
The IEL generator so.
Um.
First of all that.
To understand.
The to really understand the reflection
API of any platform.
If you remember yesterday I said I've
asked you what are the reflection support
in JavaScript and we conclude that
basically you have two constructs,
one is for.
Var and in dictionary so that you can
enumerate the keys of the dictionary and
in fact it's inspect the structure of of
of the objects.
And the second one is type of which is
something that only.
The interpreter can give you that given
the variable,
it gives you the actual type as a string
of the the value. In Java,
the reflection API gives you access to
classes, methods.
Etc. Fields, parameters of the methods,
types, etc. In.
net you have few other objects,
so in general.
Especially for compiled language,
if you have any reflection reflection
support which is not necessary.
I mean there are C has no reflection,
C++ has no reflection,
C++ has some library implementing
reflection,
but basically the language does not
provide reflection.
Raster. No. In general,
all those programming languages that want
to reduce the overhead at runtime tend to
avoid the reflection because reflection.
Comes with the extra cost.
That's specially if you want to write
system level code,
you may not want to pay and the cost is
not necessarily CPU cycles.
Because the larger cost that any.
Language has to pay is the in memory
database that you have to build to
represent all the reflection element,
all the elements that are required to
reflect to the user.
Uh, the the the uh.
The program structure, OK.
We also commented and I didn't spend much
time on this notion and I think it now
it's a good idea to bring it up again.
That in general to be able to reflect the
the execution of the current program.
You need to have the information about
the current program, OK.
So.
The.
Let me fetch.
A diagram that I'm sure I.
Mm.
OK.
So let me spend.
Few second around the.
A art of my life. There we are.
I was looking for these.
O.
In general.
This is the the diagram that stands
behind any reflection support you can
imagine. OK,
so I write my system in the programming
language.
OK, so um.
If I transform my programming,
my programmer,
I want to perceive the the transformation
as if it happens at the programming
language level.
OK if I inspect my programmer.
I wanted to talk about the types and
things that I wrote in my code.
I don't want to predicate on something
else, OK?
But in fact,
in environments such as Java or.
net in general in compiled languages,
as you can see,
I keep mentioning Java and.
net because at the end of the day we have
either C, Rust, etcetera,
so system level languages.
Or system with the runtime such as JVM
and CLR and then the rest is some
self-contained architecture with the
interpreter and just in time compiler,
but basically Python Go.
All these languages tend to come with
their own runtime. So but in any case,
if there is a level which is the level of
abstraction of my language and then I
have the target level which is.
Not equivalent. OK,
so at runtime the intermediate language
that will be executed by the virtual
machine is different than microgramming
language. Then I need to provide.
To programmer, to programmers,
the illusion of accessing the source code
of the program,
even though actually that source code
does not exist anymore.
And what made popular reflection with
Java?
Because reflection was available in small
talk, it was available in Lisp,
it was available in many, many places.
We commented that Lisp introduces quasi
quotation and quotation, etc.
So what made popular in Java was the fact
that Java was the first compiling,
I think the first compiled language that
were able to provide a reflection API
even though it was compiled and it was a
brilliant idea.
Was you know what? Uh,
in Java everything is a class at runtime.
So uh,
in the Java virtual machine there is the
notion of the class, so the class is not.
Eliminated at compile time as it happens
in C and therefore there is a subset of
the objects that defines a particular
program of the source language and.
Of the intermediate language that are
basically equivalent. OK,
and so I can give the impression to the
programmer that when it explore the
program through the reflection API, it's.
Exploring its source code rather than the
compiled version. OK,
so the choice of having a bytecode with
that retains classes, methods,
annotations on top of the.
Methods,
etcetera had a very profounding impact on
the design system after,
mostly because this idea allowed for
supports that otherwise will not be
possible.
The ability for a compiled language to
inspect part of its own structure at
runtime without having everything.
Because I mean of course I could I can
devise a a system that takes that
includes all this C code.
Inside the binary,
so I ship the executable plus a section,
the text section of the program with the
C code and I do basically what the
debugger does in the compiler code.
I have few pointers that allows me to.
Read the source code and I can show you
the source code that we all know.
When you compile the system with
debugging,
you get the stack trace with a lot of
information.
So I'm not questioning that is of course
possible, but it's impractical.
One of the reason because people like
compiling the compiling languages is to
not distribute the source code.
So clearly that was another element blah
blah blah. OK,
so but it's important to having.
In mind,
this kind of diagram in this context is
about cogeneration,
but this applies also to reflection.
So basically you you'd like to have an
API which gives the impression to operate
at the programming language level even
though.
You are operating at the intermediate
language level, OK,
and we already commented that there are
things that emerge from the binary and
that you can see through the reflection
API.
And as the compilers and the languages
gets more sophisticated and as long as
the sugaring processes take place.
You will see more and more elements in
the binary that are not present at the
language level in your program.
So we commented when in in C#.
We discussed the comprehension,
the ability to express an enumeration as
a single function with the yield
construct. If you remember,
we disassembled the.
The the compiling the version and the
result was basically a type,
a class type with a a finite state
machine which represents the the the
computation. OK.
If you enumerate the types,
you will find that type that is not
present in your program. OK,
so first of all, the most user,
the most sophisticated reflection APIs
available typically.
Allows you to see the structure of the
runtime.
The farthest is the runtime from the
source language,
the more you will feel that you're
inspecting exploring something which is
not the the the actual your program. OK.
So this is something that you always have
to keep in mind.
So one of the typical question that you
have to when you start doing reflection
processes, you have to ask yourself, OK,
what is the difference between the
runtime representation and and my
language representation?
Is that?
The farthest,
they are the less common concept they
will have to be shared. OK,
and that's that's a critical aspect when
we come to reflection and in fact Java
didn't even have.
In the reflection API,
the ability of generating code.
So basically the reflection API gave the
program the ability to inspect classes,
methods, interfaces, annotations.
And types and that's it. No code,
no way to read the bytecode of the method.
Why?
Because the bytecode is not equivalent to
the source code,
and so they decided to not expose that
part. Now if you are a compiler writer,
that's a pity.
Because it's very painful in general to
generate the physical representation of a
binary program,
you have to implement a lot of rules in
order to have a correct output from your
compiler.
So everybody was hoping to have a
reflection API for generating
intermediate language.
Something that Microsoft did with.
net and it was one of the difference why
I'm making this long introduction because
there are names in the reflection API
that you may not understand.
Because they are not related to your
program or to the object that you define,
but to some runtime elements.
Assembly in in the case of the common
language runtimes is one of these.
So in Java you will know that you.
Generate classes,
so every binary file contains the class
definition. That's it.
And this for the good and the bad.
It has nice things and bad things as a
choice.
One of you you can bundle your classes
together in a zip file,
but it's just a way to aggregate them,
to ship them, etcetera.
The jar file at the end of the day is a
zip file plus a manifest,
and so it's a it's a zip.
It's a container.
In.net, for several reason,
they decided to introduce another level
which is called the assembly,
and the assembly is the binary. OK,
so the output of the compiler is not a
binary file for each class.
It is DLL or executable,
but that's just the extension.
The binary format,
of course it was started on Windows,
implements the raw format is a variant of
the port.
Executable file,
which is a standard format,
and internally you have a database with
all the types defined in that in that
assembly. OK,
so the assembly is a group of class or
types or other elements.
In a binary format with all the metadata
that you require to be able to parse them
and to analyze them. OK,
that those informations are used by a
runtime to load the types,
but they are also.
A boundary for your programming.
So you are familiar with private.
Private means in Java private is when you
declare something private is accessible
only in the class.
Uh, protected.
Private plus inherited public everyone in.
net. You also have internal.
Internal is public but only inside the
assembly.
So the existence of the assembly is not
just a file for packaging,
is also a boundary that you feel when
you're programming so that you don't have
to assume that something that is used
publicly by your life.
Library is publicly available to the rest
of the world. OK,
so it's basically a compromise to allow a
sort of public, but only for my code,
not public for everybody else. OK,
two stupid questions. One,
the same piece that the level of or using
the?
I mean the assembly is the container of
the the intermediate language.
So basically the name of assembly is the
the binary file that contains the code.
It contains the byte code.
Methods that will be just in time
compiled by the runtime.
Classes types.
So basically it is similar to the zip
file to some extent of Java because it
collects all the classes,
but being defined organically,
technically you have a full database,
so there is when you.
Open the database,
you will find the table of the types with
all the pointers to the file where
there's some type definition starts,
etcetera, etcetera.
So it's an application of types
technically with bytecode inside,
but at the same time there are,
I don't know.
Crypto signatures are integrated in the
file, etcetera. So technically it is.
You can't see the classes,
so in the zip file you get a a bunch of
files compressed.
In this case you have a database which
represents all the types in this, OK.
And so for instance,
the byte code is in the same section for
all the methods of all the classes,
because you have the table that tells you
this byte code belongs to this method. OK,
so that's it. But this is a technicality.
I don't think it's really important,
but it's.
Really important on the other side the
the fact that this as a consequence both
in the semantic of the language because
now you have a scope of visibility of
names which is internal and is defined in
terms of this container.
And in reflection of course you have
something that for instance is Java is
not present and not is not even present
in C# because technically the assembly is
the output of the compiler.
So inside the language there is no
assembly.
I I'm not declaring an assembly,
it's just the project that I'm compiling
that will produce the assembly. OK,
and so the assembly here you perceive it
only because you're using the reflection
API,
otherwise you won't be able to perceive
this.
Now.
One of the things that.
net made available was the ability to
build an assembly.
Hmm.
So you you get the API for code
generation and this was missing in Java.
So in Java the intersection,
so the ability through the reflection API
to manipulate the state of the program.
It's limited to invoke methods or set
fields,
so you can dynamically in Java write a
program which invoke the methods.
Not because you you you wrote in your
program invoke this method,
but because you write a program that say
OK, let's find through the API.
The method invoke and call it and you can
generate the code at runtime.
So this is possible.
So you can even write a program that
invokes methods that were unknown.
Compile time. OK,
of course you pay some overhead because
you have to browse the data structure.
You can you have to assemble several
things to to obtain this,
but nevertheless it is possible,
but you can't.
Generate a class in Java through the API.
Of course there are libraries that build
this limitation,
but I mean if I look at the standard
library, it's not there.
Um.
In.
net was introduced and this has changed
quite a lot. So this is the.
net core open source version of the code
generation. It was different.
When the framework was Windows only.
There are design choices.
They try to simplify some assumption so
that it was easy to port to different
operating systems. Don't mind,
but basically the idea is there.
So the assembly name is an object which
represents the name of the assembly wall.
Then I create I create a persisted
assembly builder.
Which is the class that that we use to
generate the physical representation,
the bytes of my executable and.
OK,
and I have an assembly name and then I
have to provide.
The core assembly.
The core assembly is basically the system
library. OK,
in this way I can output a binary which
depends on a different version of the
runtime.
But these are technicality.
But it's nice because I mean,
I want to target the very same runtime
I'm using, so I don't really care. OK,
so I say OK, I use the reflection API.
I've show you, I've shown you.
That you can use get type yesterday.
You can also use the type of which is
equivalent.
The difference is that when you do dot
get type or in Java dot get class you
have an object and you ask what is the
class of this object.
In this case I have the type name,
the type name object and I wanna the.
Instance of the reflection which
represents the the object class, right?
And then I know that one of the fields of
of of the type definition is the assembly
where it is defined.
And so I use it to say, OK,
I want to create an assembly builder with
this name and with the same runtime of
the class object. OK.
There are thousands of discussion about
what is the right way,
should I expose the argument, should I,
should I not, etcetera.
So sometimes you may find verbose and you
may ask what why there is no.
Overloaded that this code automatically
and there are multiple answers to that.
OK,
so I mean I'm not going to go there now.
This assembly builder internally.
So the assembly builder is something that
is capable of creating a builder.
They're an assembly,
the assembly internally as a notion,
which in this case is.
Only for computation purpose.
So I mean it's only physical
representation.
It has no counterpart in terms of the
semantics, which is it is defined module.
So technically the assembly contains
modules which contains types.
But the module is a very old concept that
has basically no consequences.
So I mean I'm mentioning just because I'm
defining a dynamic module and so now you
know.
Let's go to more interesting use of the
reflection API.
So from the module builder,
because the assembly contains modules,
the modules contains types.
So from the module builder I say define
type.
Which is like if I'm writing class
manually in my C# file.
I provide the name of the class.
That's easy.
And I provide.
The types attribute OK because the type
is not necessary class.
There are it may be a structure in
document, a value type,
something that has.
This is not a reference type.
It's not created in the heap.
It's created as a value like integers. OK,
dotnet allows for creating also
structures that have the value semantics
and other reference.
Yeah, it's possible.
There are delegates and a few other
things that will at some point we will
discuss when we will talk about runtimes,
so.
In this case I say OK,
I label the type as a class public.
So by class WS may.
And as you can see,
we are generating binary,
but the constituent is the same as in the
source file public class WS name.
OK.
Then now that I have the type builder,
it's like a matriusk.
So assembly module type methods. OK,
everything is contained in in what is
basically a tree.
Of course we know that the same as in
Java in.net, there is the main method,
the static, which is the entry point.
So I define the method main.
We've uh uh.
Some attributes.
So in this case I have a lot of.
Enumerations.
In this case I have the method attribute
enumeration.
And so this is public and static.
So as you can see the reflection API is a
huge database with all the the
represented the binary,
the value representation of all the
traits which characterize your code.
Then of course this is a method,
so it must provide a return type void.
Public static void main.
Uh, and then?
You need the parameters,
so new type new type.
This is a syntax to create an array of
types because the arguments of a of a
method can be expressed as a as an array.
And in this case we have only one member
which is type of array of streaming.
So because the main method that other
than argument and array of stream so that
we are are so that we are used to see OK
so as you can see.
We are literally manipulating the the
type structure to create a new type
without having to do with things thanks
to the reflection API.
Notice that in this part,
apart from the module,
that honestly is an old thing.
The the the type definition,
the method definition,
even the assembly definition can be
perceived by the programmer at the C#
level.
So yes, I it's verbose,
but at the end of the day I basically
wrote another syntax for writing public
class WS mine, open brace, public static.
Void main.
Now.
We part from the source code because I
create an intermediate language generator
and that was.
This is where we part ways with the the
language, because I'm not emitting C#,
I'm emitting the.
DIA generator.
OK.
This program is a white space program is
a class of my compiler,
so we're not in the reflection space.
I parse using my parser, the program,
I create a compiler.
Now at the compiler I said OK,
can you generate?
The method because the program will be
generated in the main method of my output.
So the output would be a single class WS
main plus a main method that is.
That host body will contain the
equivalentin.
net of the of the whitespace program that
I'm compiling and so I pass the IR
generator.
So let me go to the definition of
compiler.
And again.
We keep going in the in this sort of
taking the tree structure of the
definition of the type and we keep going
in that way. So in my.
Program.
I need few local variables I need.
A stack because if you remember I did
mention,
but I mean it was just a mention the
whitespace stack because whitespace is
stack oriented machine.
The semantics of the stack is not
equivalent to the stack.
Of the intermediate language.
So I had to introduce especially a new
stack.
I can't really use the virtual machine
stack directly, so basically I say OK.
I need the the BRIL generator.
I want to declare a local.
Of type stack.
So this is like variable S stack S is the
the equivalent of C#. OK,
so this is like stack S.
That's the declaration. OK.
And then I need a couple of helpers of
type object. So this is sorry.
This is like object block one and sorry
and this is like object block 2.
OK so as you can see through the API I'm
basically generating every bit.
As if I was writing the code and even at
the declaration level,
basically I'm on par with C#.
Then here I use the reflection API.
So here I'm not generating,
I'm reading and I go to the type stack.
So through type of a stack I get the an
object which represent the stack class.
And I say,
can you give me the reflection object
which represents the method push with
this signature?
Which is push single argument with object
and I have a method info object.
Which represents the metal push of the
class stack.
OK,
I do the same for the pop and for the
peak,
which are the three operations that are
used by my implementation.
No.
I take all the instructions,
so I already passed it. I did everything.
I only have to emit and the emission
typically is the emit a number of
operation into the target language.
This is typical of any compiler, so.
So if I have to emit the push of the
white space, then I emit what? OK,
now we part from the language.
You see the difference.
Until here it was basically OK,
different syntax.
But I understand what's going on.
When you reach this place, you say, OK,
what? What is load lock?
Because here there is no direct C#
counterpart for this instruction.
That is a virtual machine instruction is
a lower level concept and C# compiler
basically.
Converts your code into this set.
It is a sort of assembly,
so this load lock loads on the open stack
a local variable,
so I'm allocating on top of the operand
stack.
The reference to the stack local variable.
Then I I load onto the operating stack.
An integer, a constant.
Which is the result of this.
Then I invoke the box operation because
it has to become an object.
So this is the equivalent of box that
Andrea mentioned on Rust,
but this happens at the runtime type at
runtime.
Because I mean invoking.
The push method and the push method
requires an object,
but I want to push an integer,
so I need to box the integer inside an
object, push the object. OK,
this is the idea.
Notice here the only thing that I provide
to the box operation is the type of the
box which is integer. Why? Because so.
Let's say.
Do you open on stack?
Here, let's say it's empty.
Uh, after this the open stack.
Contains the stack reference, OK.
After this.
There is this fix me because actually the.
White space allows to to use arbitrary
precision integers by specifying as many
bits as you want,
but I assuming that I'm using only 32
bits. OK,
so that's I'm not fully implementing the
specification of the language, but the.
For uh, so the up stack here.
Uh, we contain. Oh, good.
Thanks AI stack ref and an integer. OK,
because on top of the stack I first push
the stack reference,
then I pushed an integer which is the
value I want to push in in the stack now.
You're.
Yes, Sir.
Oh, that's nice. Yeah,
part is the comments and understands what
I'm doing in the comments.
That's interesting.
The open stack now contains because the
box what it does.
It pop.
It expects on top of the stack an integer.
It's there.
So it pops the value.
It creates the object using that value.
The equivalent of the integer plus
instance in Java and pushes on the stack
the reference to this new object.
So basically now I have the reference to
an object which contains the integer.
That's the the the core of the box
operation.
And then?
I emit a virtual call.
OK,
so now I'm calling the method which
method push M.
So this is the definition of the method
through the reflection API.
And that's it,
because the arguments will be taken from
the stack of operands and which are the
arguments.
The 1st is the argument and the 2nd is
the this pointer because push M is a.
Instance method of a class,
so you need this reference and so the
stack reference is the actual object
stack object on which I want to invoke
the push method.
And the object is the argument of the the
push method. OK,
so this happens in general with the
bytecode and.
Basically,
the operation is always the same.
You push arguments,
you push this argument,
then to all the arguments, then covert,
you unload and the result will be after
this the OP stack.
See. Oops. Oh, yes, good AI.
I'm impressed about actually because
basically the AI understood what I was
doing here and understood that after this
call the stack will be empty because you
pop the argument, you pop this,
you invoke the method.
And since it's a void method because it
has side effects,
nothing will be pushed again as a result.
So the stack is empty.
OK, so this is what's going on.
So when we first inspected this code,
we said OK barely,
we got this which emits code,
emits code using the reflection API and
as you can see this is a typical code you
end up writing.
When you use reflection,
either you browse the type system by get
type, get method, get property, get field,
whatever it is.
So you can browse the structure of your
program or.
You can generate by using the very same
model which is generating a tree.
And then the library is responsible for
when I finish this process.
Let me undo all this.
Now it's not really helpful.
OK, um, once I finished.
What is the main?
There we are.
I go to the type builder and say OK can
you create the type?
So I'm basically baking all the byte code
and say OK the meta definition is done.
Now I want to create the type and.
And then I generate uh.
The metadata and then I use a class that
I received from the reflection API that
actually generate all the the binary
itself, so.
I create the PE builder.
PE stands for portable executable,
which is the the physical representation
of the binary file.
And I add the the metadata,
I add the the the stream of.
Internet Internet language and then I
create a BLOB builder which is a binary
large object builder and then at last I
serialize.
Inside the the thing and I write all the
content to a particular file, OK.
The orig notice that the original API,
it was like assembly build the right. OK,
so all these lines that you see were not
present because the original reflection
API.
Assuming you you create an assembly,
you can write it to the file which may be
a reasonable assumption.
But then when you want to do more
sophisticated thing that that would be
complicated.
So they basically unpack it all the
processing to all these.
Classes.
So you have several places where you can
do extra things that were impossible
before. OK,
so when you comply against some
complicated API, in general,
this is not because there is some civic
behind the API which asks for more work
from you.
But it's just the need to have enough
control for specific use cases,
and it's fairly natural to witness APIs
that start easy and gets complicated and
and and so on. OK.
OK, so.
We.
Are are left with.
1.
Final but really important example of
meta programming. OK,
so so far we said OK,
meta programming can be performed by
generating the string of my program.
If I am in an interpreted world,
I can evolve the string. That's it.
OK, and that's possible.
And of course if I eval then that string
of code will have access to the
environment of my program and so I can
insert preference to my my variables and
this is.
The most basic form of meta programming
advantage is very flexible,
disadvantage syntax error and
inconsistent code is very likely to
happen. There are also security concern.
Which I am overlooking,
but security is important.
Uh.
How many of you have a?
I heard about SQL injection attack.
Yeah, I knew it. What it is?
So basically you say if I assume that the
programmer that will generate the the
code to the database.
Is a programmer that writes a code such
as var. I know bar is the parameter.
Coming from the web,
OK and then you say OK S equal select the
no. The typical thing is S from P.
Where F is equal bar.
This is a typical code that the
programmer can write.
That's nice because if I I'm lucky enough
to find this,
which is very likely all the filters.
Are typically written this way.
Then I if I'm a good hacker and can say
OK, far is, I don't know, she's the Nino,
which is the argument.
That will be attached to to the to the no.
So sorry,
let's let's use that because otherwise
it's different.
Let me use 2025 which is the year of the
filter and then I can add the insert into.
TAB values and blah blah OK.
So basically an attacker may exploit the
fact that you are string training things
to insert extra code in your program that
will be evaluated in this case by your
database.
And this is the core of a SQL injection.
By the way,
these days everybody's talking about
prompt injection because many,
many programs are using AI and so.
You can say, OK,
let's assume that this will be passive to
a model.
So let me insert some instruction,
unwanted instruction in the model by
typing in extra extra things. OK,
so this is another effect of.
Manipulating code as a string,
you may also be prone to this kind of
attack.
So because there is no type checking,
there's no way to to know that that
string is not just the number you were
you're waiting for.
Next.
Right,
so we said this is for string
manipulation. Then we said OK Lisp.
Since in Lisp everything is a list.
And lots of parentheses.
Then Lisp introduces this idea that I can
quote the list,
and in that case the list will not be
evaluated by the interpreter,
but you can pass it around and eventually
evaluate advantage.
At least you're sure that the list.
The S expression of the lisp is
syntactically correct. OK.
Now we said OK we we took F sharp as an
example in F sharp quotation which allow
quotation and quasi quotation syntax.
In this case I can even type check
because the F sharp compiler knows about
types.
And if you try to generate code which
violate the type system,
you will get an error even if you are
quoting the code. OK,
and so all these are basically
restrictions.
Of the code generation to get some
properties. So string maximum flexibility,
maximum risk.
The more complicated these the quotation
support,
the more the less flexibility you will
get, the more.
Safety you will receive. OK,
quotation is a general purpose mechanism
that allows you to quote general code.
That's not the only option. Oh,
by the way, and we said in this example.
That basically the compiler the sugars.
The quotation into a data structure which
represents the the quotation that later
you can browse to compile or interpret as
we we see with this our custom eval
implementation.
Before the end of the class,
please remind me that I have to show you
one thing.
I forgot to do it at the beginning.
So now last but not least as they say.
Let's go back to eligiate source code.
Elisa is full of interesting programming
patterns. When I developed it,
I I used a lot of these things.
Let me go into the controllers.
Let me go into the API.
And let me let's welcome the.
Link.
No, no, I'm looking for. There we are.
To the for a link that I briefly
mentioned yesterday,
but now it's time to spend a little bit
more time in understanding what really is
this. OK.
So link language integrated query is a
way to provide inside the programming
language a syntax which has no semantics.
Clearly it has the semantics.
I mean because if the semantics will be
provided by some external provider,
but since I said that I want to select
something,
I expect that this will select something.
OK, so.
The language is there's not mandate that
we implement the semantics,
but clearly you are expecting from the
provider that some semantics will be
satisfied.
But technically that's not. OK,
so the language.
So now we we went back to the compiler to
the language definition.
Basically these sugars we learned that
this the sugaring is much more common
than you may have taught before.
Before this course,
the sugars to another source code OK,
but basically allows me to express SQL
like syntax access,
so the current access to a collection OK.
They did something reasonable because
honestly see the the sequel was really
bad inside because you say select water
from but when you say well select water.
You don't know yet from where and until
the query is not fully defined,
you will typically be unable to to
completion because there's not no,
there's not known the source code.
And so you have to wait. In fact,
many SQL query writer select,
start from and then go back and
substitute the start with the name of the
field so you get the type checking. OK,
so that's.
Bad design error in the in the in the in
the sequel.
So they tried to to speak a little bit
the the approach and say OK from see in
this collection.
OK,
from C in this collection where the
election of K is equal to the ID selector
C So this in in will be combined to
select C from a politician commission
where.
K is equal to ID.
Basically the same thing. OK,
the interesting thing about this string
is that it's just the request to the
compiler to produce a data structure
which implements a standard interface.
And by itself is unable to do anything.
Now let's ask a map how this link
expression will be the sugar red the.
Got it in C#.
So while we hope to get a reasonable
effort from the AI.
OK.
I hate these stuff.
English.
American way of excelling. You're good.
Time to time is too much, nevertheless.
Find little sugary form is varquery.
Under score context dot polling station
Commission which is basically the
collection dot where.
Lambda.
dot select Lambda.
OK, so as you can see under the hood,
the functional aspects keep popping up
even in AC sharp programming language
where that didn't start as a function
with functional elements.
They were in use it like in the in the.
OK. Oh, by the way,
for those of you that are curious.
Where and select the.
So where, which is clearly a method,
technically it's not a method of the
class pollination Commission.
Awesome.
They have our, um,
metals that are attached.
By the programming name.
So they are called extensions methods in
C#.
So basically you can define a static
method somewhere else. Sorry,
Giuseppe the.
Ask GPT in between. OK,
so this square is basically a static
method defined in a library and it is
described as an extension method.
So basically.
The language gives you the impression
that you can invoke this word method on
on a.
Objects of some kind as if it was a
method of that class. OK,
so you can add the methods to existing
classes, even compile classes.
Technically you don't have access to the
private members nor the protected members.
OK,
so if you like using a a starting method
that takes as the first argument at this
point. So it's just syntactic sugar again.
OK, so this attached method implements.
The where Peter and and applies to all
the collections so you can use the the
links in that set.
Even not on database,
but just on ordinary collection in memory.
OK.
As long as you have the ability to give a
a meaning to these singers.
In general.
Um.
These.
You can get the the expression.
So the structure which represents the
query then will be passed to a driver
that says please can you combine this
into SQL?
So if you are implementing the Postgres
driver, it's available.
You will get the SQL,
the Post SQL version of the query.
If you use the Oracle provided,
you will get Oracle PLSQL if you have so
typical driving model. OK,
so the compiler basically the sugars that
syntax.
Into a data structure.
And this data structure will be browsed
to provide a different syntax depending
on this object here,
which is the collection that you want to
browse OK.
And this allows for extensible model for
a declarative syntax inside the language.
Who expressed that?
Queries in a.
In a flexible way and so also this is a
form of meta programming because
technically you are producing a data
structure that at runtime you want to
expect and you want to convert into a
collection.
Technically the result the the type
return by this is.
And I quitable.
OK.
So that is not.
It is an object which represents a source
that can be prepared for retrieving data
of some type.
OK.
Before I forget and then.
We start with the final part.
Remember yesterday when I told you beware,
we run into.
An hallucination.
It was this example, let X equal 10,
put it is X + 5 and the output supposed
by the A I was a data structure which
included the let X.
And I told you yesterday,
this is an hallucination. OK,
I didn't think, honestly,
that it would have been interesting.
So I did it yesterday evening.
I didn't think that it would have been a
nice idea to actually run the code.
Let's do it.
All right. OK, so the output is.
Uh.
Quote quoted is of type quotation
expression of integer.
So this means this is a quotation of an
expression and the return is an integer
value.
This is the inferred type by the F sharp.
It is called op addition.
And.
There is get the value of the property
called X. OK,
so as you can see it's very different
than the output of the AI.
I didn't look for this,
but this is a good example of
hallucination and.
The reason?
Because you have to pay really attention
to the output of the A I,
because it seems so natural that even I
almost got treated by the A I.
But then I said, oh,
that's impossible because a quoted value
can't include something that is outside.
Side of the court.
So this is not possible. OK,
and that was the reason because beware,
this is not right. But as you can see,
most of the time the AI is right, so it's.
Difficult to pay always attention.
You tend to trust something that most of
the time is right,
but you can get huge errors in in in the
output and this is the example so.
OK.
I thought that that would have been
interesting. All right.
First of all.
Any questions about this?
Or cons.
Did you ever use the the Reflection API
in your program, Sir?
Example.
We.
TypeScript is different but link,
yes link is is is similar.
As you see many many features of the
language tend to be copied from one to
the other.
And we're basically creating a bit
language by merging all the languages
together and that's it. Nevertheless,
I hope you appreciate how delicate it is
the balance between what?
Is compilable from what is not.
I mean in Java we said OK,
in the binary we retain types. Nice idea,
not methods, OK.
In Python you need all the source code at
runtime.
Basically there are example of Python
compilers,
but no Python compiler is fully
compatible, compatible with C Python,
so there are only approximations.
I don't Python, for instance, is a.
net implementation implementation of
Python, which compiles for.net.
But there are parts of the language that
are not covered. Why?
Because if you want to implement the eval,
you need to interpret. That's it. OK,
so it's true.
That languages keep copying on each other,
but the choices of what you allow in the
language or not will determine also the
performance. So yesterday,
from a different angle with respect of
the tradition, I briefly.
Introduce to you the the idea that in
principle the arguments of a function
invocation may be evaluated before the
invocation or only when the the parameter
is used.
Which is lazy,
eager versus lazy evaluation.
And we said OK with quotation,
we can recover the lazy evaluation but
under control,
not by using inside the language.
This makes it more efficient,
the language, the language implementation.
Drastically. OK, right. So final,
I think very important example.
Now I'm resorting to the AI and I'm
hoping that this thing will work.
Can you generate a very simple example?
Of AC program that browses a type class
and generate the.
Um, HTTP wrapper for the methods.
Uh, with the.
A custom attribute.
ITTP get and Http://post.
Pizza.
Be smaller for the class.
I hope with this will not get thing for
implementation.
OK.
There we are.
Hmm.
Looks like.
OK,
let's see and commend the output being
suspicious for hallucinations.
So what I asked is.
Basically what many libraries,
including Python, do.
I want to expose my type as a Web API.
I mean,
Web API became popular mostly because of
reflection,
because it became suddenly easy to write
your program and have some meta program
that given an input,
the class API generates a web interface
to its methods, OK.
So probably class my APII want to be able
to label.
We already commented custom attributes
are a way to add extra annotation to the
metadata of the object in in this case
the method.
So a lobe will be annotated with cat.
The.
Hello returns a string,
so hello world that will be returned and
and and the attributes are actually this
is correct are classes which you know is
from a system attribute which is a so all
the custom attributes in the.
Otherwise you can't use it as a notation.
OK, so that's a rule, so.
Now I get the type.
Oh.
Of the the type representation of my APA
class.
And and say OK for each.
Method M in methods.
For all the public instance methods.
So basically we are filtering all the
methods of my API type looking only for
public and instance.
If I have some.
HTTP get attribute. OK,
this is how you can check and dot get
customer attribute type of the attribute
and if you get something different than
null the this particular method has been
annotated with HTTP get.
Then you write line get name of the
method.
And and and the call of the method,
because I mean this is an example that
it's not including the web part, OK,
but honestly that that is not a problem.
If you develop the web server,
it's fairly easy. You receive and you can.
Either generate or invoke depending on
the approach. Same applies to the poster.
Um.
This join here.
That's interesting.
OK,
you see how the AI can over fit or so
actually OK, it's an example,
but in general you don't know the
arguments of a method, so in this case.
The generated code assume that if it's
labeled the HTTP get,
then the matter will have no arguments.
If it's supposed,
it will get all the arguments,
which makes no sense honestly.
But nevertheless and then you output post
etcetera.
So when you execute you will get get a
low will call my API dot a low and post.
Equal string message will be calling my
API dot X. OK,
why this example is important?
Because and honestly I I will say thanks
to AI.
It's a very interesting example because
it's the core of any Web API wrapper
generator. Of course,
if you go and explore.
All the web servers are now open source,
so it's fairly easy.
You can inspect and check how it works,
but basically the core will be always
this. You get the type,
you browse the methods,
you filter the methods depending on
interesting attributes that may be.
Maybe public and instance or custom and
then you decide what to do given that
type. OK, that's the typical code.
That uh.
You will write or you will make generator
for browsing and making useful things
from the methods. This is what.
The code that I began with yesterday,
yesterday is doing.
In the program, so the builder,
the host builder which is used in the asp.
net framework.
There's this basically I give to the web
builder the type startup.
The web builder will perform.
Type of startup.
We'll get the type and we'll start
browsing and say is there create service
method? Then let's invoke it.
Is there this other method? Let's do it.
OK, so at the end of the day.
That is the core of the code that you end
up writing when you wanna meet a
programmer in the in the modern world.
Of course this is the.net version.
The Java version is very similar.
If you have no reflection,
you can't do it.
And in fact I don't think that there are
so many web framework in Rust because web
is basically string processing and and so
it's a nightmare to do it in C or on or
in in Rust or similar languages.
But in Python you have similar patterns.
Of course in in Python you have other
option to label methods and function,
but basically the idea is always the same.
You basically write a program that takes
as input.
Another program part of itself,
technically explore and do something.
One of the most popular application is
the web, of course,
because we keep going in writing code
from and to the web.
Oh, I forget to to let me mention.
Of course,
since I'm doing this code here and I'm
exploring the Web API,
I can even go farther. So for instance,
if I decided to say OK.
This the method echo takes as input an
integer instead of a string.
Then when you receive the web request to
the echo and you don't get an integer.
You can.
You will generate the code that tries to
convert the argument to an integer,
and if you fail, you raise an exception.
No SQL injection.
OK, so the web has become really popular,
but that's not the only application.
There are a lot of programs that are
developed like this in database.
Because if you think the database defines
a data structure and then you have to.
Obtain a a similar data structure in your
programming language.
So typically you use a lot of reflection
to generate wrappers for your database so
that you can keep on writing my my table
dot field name equal and then the insert
or the update statement would.
Be generated for you by the same
machinery and so on.
So in general the database wrapper are
known as ORM,
Object Relational Mapping and which
basically are meta programming here which
states as input the definition.
From the database,
generate a bunch of classes and given the
classes,
they explore the data model and generate
SQL statement to automate things for you.
Link has been probably the most
successful implementation of this concept,
but it's not the only one. There are many.
Others in many other languages and if you
look for your system,
if you need to access the database,
you will look for another library that
will perform this kind of things and.
To pay the.
Likely for Andrea next class.
At some point we started writing this
code. I already said this yesterday,
but let me stress it again.
We started writing this code for one.
Essential reason types inheritance,
polymorphism, parametric polymorphism,
inheritance, polymorphism,
all the algebra to reuse go through types.
Software of few limitation.
One of these is that the type system
should be coherent and this is easy in
the same project.
It's basically enforceable in multiple
projects and and so the ability to hook.
In in types with less restriction than
type operators allow to write more
flexible runtimes.
OK and so eventually these.
So passive classes and interfaces as the
main way to do things,
which does not mean that they are useless
is that this goes on top and in fact as
you seen is I define a class with.
Methods, et cetera, et cetera,
because class are still useful.
But basically through reflection you can
be more direct in the operation without
having to cope with the restriction of
the typing model, which can be.
Of course you pay something, but clearly.
If you are generating HTTP wrappers,
a TCP connection is done.
An SSL encrypted the channel is
established.
You encrypt and encrypt things. Of course,
browsing the types through reflection is
API is basically neglectable with.
With respect to the rest, OK,
so in all the situation in which you
perform so much operations,
it's not that inefficient to use the
reflection API, and that's a good point.
Clearly,
if you want to do a Monte Carlo system,
this would be a suicide because basically
you will slow down significantly your.
In that case, we will not use reflections,
OK.
Nice. So I think we can stop here.
Thank you. No, it was the hallucination.
I I was worried to forget about that. OK.
Thank you.